{
  "reference_number": "11565",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Act local, Think Global. Cheap Carbon Credits have given us a decade of deforestation, uncertainty, and avoidance. Planning to\n purchase carbon units from overseas suggests we are planning to avoid changes. NZ can benefit from selling international carbon\n\n units. Do NOT purchase overseas credits."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Circumstances will always change. Parliament can always change the Zero Carbon Bill regardless of this \"position\" question achieving\n Zero Carbon earlier than 2050 will not require the Zero Carbon Bill target to be changed."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "no proposed \"borrowing\" from future budgets"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "\"exceptional circumstances\" always exist eg \"Natural Disaster\" arising from Climate Change? Dont Change the target - solve the\nproblem."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - your Page44 comments appear to undervalue the cost to NZ of missing our international committements. Being a \"net polluter\"\n\nwill devalue NZ inc. Budget setting must include the positive benefits to NZ, environmental leadership, and a strong Brand NZ."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "NZ Business, in particular Agriculture sector MUST be on board. Clear pricing signals to help long term planning - eg \"Kiwirail main\ntrunk de-electrification/carbonisation\" Strong committment to mitigate delaying tactics from Carbon exploitative industries. Champion\n\ncompanies and individuals, celebrate those who have achieved the goals. with respect to sea-level rise and climate change effects as\npart of the ZCBill :- Figure out how to stop insurance industry from contracting out of obligations due to CCC formal risk assessments.\nFigure out how to maintain at-risk land and structures as productive. Local Government NZ harmonisation with Zero Carbon Bill risk\n\nassessment and adaption plan Changes to Resource Management Act , Local Government Act, Environment Acts etc as required."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In addition challenge Science NZ to be ACTIVE in measuring NZ and Overseas emissions. Ensure the reduction gains are real or\nChallenge the Science and process."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "CCC must be covered by OIA processes and report transparently to NZ NZ Government to implement or justify deviation"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Commissioners to publish their individual Carbon Footprint (eg 5 trips to Zurich, or saved due to skype)"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Risk Assessment, and adaptation plan. Climate Change Commissioners to get local government working together"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Ability to REWARD$$ high performing individuals, companies, councils with say small% of CO2-e saved, subject to verification/peer-\nreview and national publicity..."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "NZ to be THE Global leader. Zero net 2050 requires a change - Business as usual will result in more junk ukrainian credits or the next\n\nversion of that, and Kiwirail Diesel quality planning processes. I do not purchase US products due to their position on the Paris\nAccord. NZ cant afford to be a global polluter. Zero Net 2050 must also include planning for a) Science now says 2050 is too\nconservative 2040? 2030? and HOW TO IMPLEMENT if required. b) climate change refugee's and displacement - internal and from the\n\nlow countries. Thank you for your efforts."
    }
  ]
}
